No, my friends, after we have learned about the bubble sort algorithm in the previous videos, let's
implement this algorithm and see and in the next exercise, we are going to implement the bubble sort
in Java and let's learn about that complexity, the time and the space complexity of this algorithm
and try to make optimization for this bubble sort of algorithm.
First of all, we include the S3, the IO detach, and we try to create a method that we imparts to
party me.
There's two numbers.
So we are swiping the first and no value with the second and the second with the first, so we create
a void swab.
Its role is to swab that the X do Y and Y to export that.
We have learned in early exercises in this course how to make this swiping swiping.
So swiping will make for it will make will be done by creating a temp temporarily and that took the
value of X and stored it inside this temp variable and assigned the X to Y and assigned the Y to tap.
This is the three steps three course three lines that we are going to make in order to swap the two
elements.
Now let's create the bubbles sort algorithm by creating a method called Void Bubbles Sort Int Array.
It took into their perimeters the array that we are going to sort, and the end how many numbers.
So and I and J that we are going to use in there for loops.
These four loops acts as that the balance that we have seen in that in the animation before.
So.
Four are equal to zero I less than and minus one and I plus plus.
So we are going to move from zero to all the numbers from zero to and minus one considering through
all the elements by plus plus.
So the last I elements are already in the place.
We have learned in the previous videos that when we move their elements, we are going to move at the
first step at the first iteration, like iterating through all the elements and reaching the end.
We have moved them minimum elements inside the nine elements, which is one, and we have moved it to
that extreme left.
So we have considered that one is the element that is already sorted.
Then we have moved again in a second second step that goes through all the iterations through all their
remaining eight elements, and we have moved the number two to become near to one before one or shortly
after one.
So we have considered one and two are sorted and we do the same thing until we reach that nine elements.
So guys, think about it if we need to conserve the elements and preserve them and take them as sort
that we need to use in another loop that starts from zero do and minus one minus I.
So I list I elements.
If we consider that we have and we have made and reserved one element and we have sorted one element,
so we need M minus one element C because we are not going to go through that sorted elements.
And this is what we have been in that animation before.
So please go back to the previous video and see how this algorithm in details and fully animated function
works.
If every at index greater than a rate at index +1.
So if the preceding and if the elements that the left is greater than the element to the right, then
make a swap.
So we are going to swap this element by referring the index for this and the reference for that.
This element, the second element at a rate at index +1.
And then they say, OK, this is the bubble.
Sort this very simple, but you need to make that and minus one and end minus ie minus one.
This is the trick, and we need to create a sweeping and method that creates a sweeping function that
the functionality to this bubble sort until we need it.
So printing that everyday, it's very simple.
We have this exercise in the early exercises.
We use AI from zero to size.
That is fast and we print all the address.
OK.
All right.
In order to test our bubbles for algorithm, I want from you to put this code in that your compiler
c compiler.
And I want from you also to read the inputs and put the outputs here in the comments below in order
to make discussion and feel free to if you have any question, any comment coming, any recommendation,
any suggestion for this course or this lesson.
So please, I'm happy to see this and I want from you to do a favor for me to rate us five stars who
need me.
So supporting us is very beat will make a very big difference for me and.
Well, may I have a receipt to make the scores the largest course on the Earth?
And we are going to create many, many courses, so and main array, we create an array.
This is an array containing seven elements seven numbers.
We start by and size of array over size of array of index zero and bubble sort.
Array.
We passed this array to be sorted and we pass that and number of elements.
OK.
Then we print assorted array and we print out the array at index.
We have that, we have that we have passed and as the size of this, so we have sorted the array, we
have printed the array and returning so beautiful to me.
So this is the bubble sort algorithm inside.
But there is one problem.
Let's talk about that complexity.
The above function always runs to any square because we have to array it to loops here.
So this is the first loop if this is the outer loop and this is the inner loop.
So every time we have, this is for n minus one and this for n minus II minus one and times and is and
square.
So the complexity of this algorithm is still in the best case as well.
And the square, because we need to go through all the elements to make sorting.
So if we pass a sorted array, it would still off and the square.
This can be optimized by stopping the algorithm if inner loop didn't cause any swap.
So if if the array is sorted, why we are going to loop through all these two loops and to check if
this array and make the that things happens as if it is not a sorted array.
So we need to make a check for optimized bubble sort algorithm in order to be a professional and and
a mate.
And like a professional coder and professional algorithm, algorithmic production or producer.
Yes.
So.
We start the same include and include the studio would create this weapon, the same thing, but here
in the bubble sort, I will method.
I will make a small change.
I will create a Boolean swab.
Here, hold the swab in the same way I will create two arrays.
I will start making the swap equal to false initializing at two folds.
And this is the inner loop.
So if IRA J at Index J Equal Array at greater than a rate at Index J +1, then maybe the swab and put
this swept through.
This will indicate that we have made a swap, but.
If there is no sweat, if the array is considered as as sorted, so we need to check if no two elements
were swept by inner loop, then break.
So if swept equal equal to falls, then break.
This is very important.
We go through elements one time to check if they are sorted or not, if they are sought to them to break.
So we are not increasing the complexity of this.
This algorithm, a from a from end to end is square.
We are reducing this.
This algorithm by from and the square to an in case of that array is sort this out of the same as before.
So the bubble sort of algorithm complexity now becomes in the words and the average case time complexity
would be Oh, and the square.
So the worst case occurs when the error rate is reverse sorted.
OK, reverse sorted.
So we are going to sort all the elements.
So we are we have nine five nine eight six seven nine eight seven six five four three two one.
We are going to increase them into we sort them into the increasing order.
One two, three, four, five, six and seven, eight, nine and 10.
So this is the worst case in the bubble sort algorithm.
Best case time complexity is all of em.
So best case occurs when the array is already sorted.
We have decreased that on the square to all end time complexity because we have added so.
This function, this condition, if is swept this check, we are making this boolean swab and we checked
if we have made a swab.
So if there is no swab, then then then our array being sorted and no need to make or and squished,
it would be the best case scenario.
I'm.
Time complexity.
In terms of space complexity, it's very simple, it's all of one.
So this is what we have learned about the bubble algorithm and we have learned about the time and space
complexity and how to make and optimize our bubbles fourth algorithm and see.
Now let's move to that.
Add to that Java IBD Java compiler, and let's implement.